I guess both of us would be kind of
described as IDW adjacent would you like
to I just like if you could just talk
about your your own background for a for
a bit what's your bio oh sure I mean I'm
used to just say documentary filmmaker
cuz that seemed to mean something in the
world I'm not sure what it means but
that you know I come from the
independent documentary filmmaking world
went to school for for film started I
guess asking more let's call it I DW ish
political questions in college when 9/11
hit when I was a sophomore and that
really started a lot of the gears in my
mind moving in the direction of maybe
where certain questions have have come
out and finally a couple years ago just
Dovan after sort of frustration was
boiling over and reached out to a group
that was hosting Sam Harrison Maajid
Nawaz and Australia the things moved
pretty quickly and suddenly we were
making a documentary based on the
collaboration between Majid and Sam and
and I guess that alerted you know my
presence to some some IDW folks and
whatever this word means is that I'm
sure we'll talk about it I don't know
the word now I guess when people ask me
what I do and I say content creator it
sounds really thin but I guess that's
what it is I'm a content creator in the
philosophical and intellectual space so
that's podcasts and documentary that's a
few of us around
yeah whatever we are you know anything
that moves and makes noise and has
pictures we kind of touch and and
hopefully try to do some good with it so
yeah we're in the same boat there but I
guess we're pointing our cameras at some
some ideas that would be considered IDW
so that makes us literally adjacent to
it in many cases yeah yeah Jason enough
to be able to say it in film it let's
put it that way yeah and hopefully
adjacent enough that hopefully people
like us do our homework a little bit
which means you're gonna have to expose
yourself to these ideas and and see the
what's good about them what's bad about
them try to poke around at the dangers
hopefully take sort of a critical eye to
some of the ideas because presumably we
we care about them and in some in some
way do you have a definition for the IDW
or for the wider I mean I sort of look
at it
as the IDW is the named part of a
broader movement and and it's sort of
maybe you have to disentangle those
things as well to see what is the
emergent phenomenon that the IDW is the
sort of named part of yeah I I don't
know actually and then this is why it
becomes so hard to talk about when the
definition is so you know loose to begin
with I have what I wish it would be I
think even burying that initial article
sort of pondered what I want it to be is
this what I want it to be is people who
are connected by their common pursuit of
truth and unafraid to ask taboo or let's
call it politically uncorrect questions
to find that truth that could be you
know it's people who are unafraid to
wander into the waters of IQ and race or
religion and violence and you know these
things that sort of make people cringe
you know everyone says famously when you
get at the dinner table don't talk about
politics or religion this is a group of
people who are like we're gonna talk
about politics and religion because it
matters and we're trying to get
somewhere but that pursuit if it's a
pursuit of truth in some sort of
abstract way that's there's something
I've written about but that's a
philosophical pursuit trying to find
truth and where I think it can there the
cracks that are showing in the IDW that
I worry about is if it becomes a
political movement i define them very
distinctly that philosophical effort is
one where you're seeking to find truth
again just sort of agnostic lis just
truth for its own sake and then the
political movement is trying to figure
out how to be effective which is which
is agnostic of truth you could be the
worst person in the world like Pol Pot
you know that regime was very political
I obviously disagree with their
philosophical precepts but they figured
they were figuring out how to move
people from point A to point B and you
could do it with progressive movements
or any movement and if the IDW becomes
you know the difference between being a
journalist and an activist is a really
interesting conversation and if it if it
becomes politicians rather than
philosophers in that mindset then then I
think it's rightful to attack it and I
think the cracks will probably crumble
it in some ways you sort of pretend like
no one's listening
pretend like you're not going to get in
trouble for the questions you asked
there we see that that that's probably
naive which is why it inherently has to
become a little political because people
are watching and so your words matter
and there is no matter how philosophical
you want to be there is always a bit of
a a risk to saying things publicly even
anything I say here I assume it will be
seen and so having just a let's call it
a moral filter on what you say is is
probably a good thing for all of us to
ponder but I think the IDW if it was
anything was a recognition that that
filter had gotten so thick that people
were just self censoring themselves in
these extreme ways and it really
mattered particularly the the
acceleration of it after 9/11 where
where I jumped into it with the film I
made was I think noticing that that
filter was so thick that it was actually
doing real real damage and we could be
headed and maybe we are now you know
with the Trump moment we could talk
about maybe we we have wandered into
those waters where the filter actually
was counterproductive
so hopefully the IDW is dissolving the
filter and you know seeing what we find
but I worry that it's failing to live up
to that potential and a lot of a lot of
circles a mutual friend of ours
Ryan Bennett I think came up with
something I think really really useful
called the IDW protocol and I might and
I might flash that up on screen he's got
it pinned to his Twitter bio but it's
three principles that I think are as
good as anything as to defining what the
IDW protocol as a kind of method of
interacting rather than a Content it is
brilliantly what do you what do you make
of that if I could pick up some of the
like platform and incentive things
because it's interesting I didn't go
through the newsroom like you did I was
always sort of in the independent world
and in my world it was I would see I
think the kinds of things that you saw
daily only at the end of my process
usually at the end of my process like I
would make a whole film and sort of be
on an island maybe I would have some
investors who really just believed in
what I was doing or the story was sort
of you know angel money and in the end
when you're talking to distributors and
where you're gonna show this thing
that's when suddenly all of these other
incentives I was like oh wait like you
need commercials and like
this needs to be a certain length and
all those other factors that you know
you were running into in the newsroom
it's like the incentives here you have
30 seconds for a soundbite and you
better make it good all that kind of
stuff and yeah and so I I was exposed to
it at a very different part of the
pipeline then you were in in our sort of
media upbringing but I think it's a
really important point maybe to linger
on about the dangers I know this is
something we'll wait into more but
you're talking about the innocent sort
of start of like I just want to have
different conversations and I'm really
dissatisfied with what I'm seeing and
sort of the mainstream or my friends are
talking about and kind of afraid to talk
about that's not it's like a great like
innocent little kind of thing but you
know you start to pick up steam and
pretty soon you have people watching and
then pretty soon there's people with
money and then pretty soon there's
commercials and pretty soon it's like
there's this habit and humanity of you
want to like reinvent the wheel every
time but we always keep just
like rebuilding the same thing that we
oh that we tore down and I think we're
in the IDW maybe someone like Rogan that
you mentioned or all the other names
that I'm sure will get into eventually
start to feel the pressure of these
incentives that we feel like we got away
from and some people have been really
successful about about they're lucky I
think but about getting away from those
incentives of like we're not gonna be ad
based and maybe models like just user
patreon kind of stuff is a way to break
out of that model maybe it is we're all
trying to sort of figure it out but this
I think you're hinting at sort of the
phenomenon of audience capture of the
the feedback loop certainly of financial
gain when you do something and suddenly
your wallet grows and then you just
start to tend to do that thing again and
wherever the psychology comes into that
process of sort of you know knowingly
well I'm going to repeat the process or
you just start feeling good because of
your wallet and then the story emerges
in your mind and you're doing some post
hoc rationalization that's dangerous
stuff I mean we obviously we've seen it
all the news media that the channels
seemed to split further more extreme and
more you know further left and further
and it incentivizes if the mandate is
just get viewers get clicks we know sort
of where that could lead it'll amplify
maybe the darkest parts of our
psychology that get addicted to outrage
and all this kind of stuff that we see I
think it would be really naive to
pretend that starting a YouTube channel
with the intention of not of escaping
all that means you will have
successfully escaped it it will chase
you and it will find you and it's and
it's real it's real potent dangerous
stuff and I think we should have a level
of not apologetics for someone who falls
in prey to it but sympathy for them and
I'm sure we can name names of the people
who may have fallen prey to that but we
should also admit that that that stuff
is like old old psychology that everyone
deals us on a personal day-to-day level
of sort of the ends justify the means
it's like well I worked all day at
Auschwitz but I got paid you know like
that's the extreme version of it but you
go to your job and you do your thing and
maybe you're participating in some kind
of system that that you know has some
moral cost to it but in the end the ends
justify the means and I I think it's
it's a dangerous it's a dangerous way to
live again it's nothing new it's it
happens in every sort of field that we
see in sort of an open capitalist
society that we always have to contend
with because you know it's it's
attractive it's attractive even just
getting the likes even if you're not
making any money and in this sort of
conversation but you get a bunch of
retweets and likes I think we all check
our notifications and we all have to
admit the dopamine hit that we see when
we see a high number is is a real thing
that we have to contend with yeah I mean
I certainly feel that myself
like like I just just the fact that
there is a comment thread and knowing
what the audience like and what they
don't like you can I mean if you you
have to not be human to not to not feel
that in some way yeah yeah yeah I feel
it too and I think we should be honest
about that and be able to laugh at it a
little bit and I think to sort of zoom
out a little bit of you know you and I
have talked a lot before and I keep
coming back to this line
of the danger the dangers that lurk in
something like the IDW conversation or
even followers and fans of it is you
know once this mistake that I've come to
to notice or basically profess is that
there seems to be a trend of people who
think the moment that they have rejected
bad philosophy or a bad philosophy it
also means they've rejected bad
psychology and they really have nothing
to do with each other so you know if you
find this maybe in a way like I did
through like an atheist conversation and
you you think you're so brilliant cuz he
rejected some carpenter zombies story
2,000 years ago and and you know now you
think oh I've solved the world and I'm
all set
great it's true you've projected one
really dumb bad idea and you could get
deep into that but it doesn't mean
you're not susceptible to the Lords of
status and sex and money and all of
these other things and even some if
someone rejects a political leaning
being like oh I've noticed that the left
is really wacky and it's gone overboard
and look like I'm I woke to this in sort
of the red pill way or either side of
that if whether whatever your political
epiphany is that doesn't mean you've
escaped the normal trappings that we all
deal with of weak psychology and and
they relate but they don't they don't
they don't correlate the way that I
think a lot of people tend to to jump
the gun and think they have and that
goes for the personalities in the IDW
that goes for the big names that we all
know who are on stage that goes for
people like you and I who are trying to
sort of tell the story of these people
go through people following it I think
we all have to just sort of be honest
about that again laugh about it a little
bit it's if there's anything that binds
us as humans together that would be a
great thing to sort of you know find
common ground even with your political
enemy is like we're all susceptible to
these kind of things we should admit
that and then what you do with it is is
really important because I think there
that's a huge moment in a personal life
that's a huge moment in a political or
philosophical movement are you going to
reject that part of psychology and do
everything you can to suppress it and
and overcome it and reach some kind of
Nirvana to use like a religious term
that's that's an effort that a lot of
people take on and maybe success
or are you going to admit that these are
trappings that not only even calling
them trappings might be too negative
these are facets of a human psychology
that can actually be beautiful and
provide a lot of meaning and we need to
figure out a way to massage them and
maybe hijack them for ethical ends it's
the word actually a good word to sort of
ponder with it is virtue signaling I
hate when people use the word virtue
signaling it's something we do and of
course we've see sort of the really
disingenuous version of it the virtue
signaling that's just like over the top
and clearly just makes your eyes roll
the way I just sort of did on camera but
I think we should all admit that we all
we're always virtru signaling and some
in some way and there's a there's an
ability that again it's the same choice
are you gonna just try to deny that you
virtue signal and that any one virtue
signals and this should be something
that we stamp out in sort of human
psychology if we're gonna make any
progress or do you recognize it as a as
a maybe even necessary but permanent
feature of human psychology that we just
have to not even contend with but take
care of and make sure it's amplified
towards ethical ends that I think that's
a really really interesting
philosophical split and psychological
split that I don't know I could like pin
IDW characters in either direction on
that split but it's a split we don't
talk about often enough because we just
sort of deny that you I think everyone
assumes the right answer is to reject
this stuff and just put it and make fun
of it and it's like I don't know I I
think that'll probably that'll probably
be the snake eating its own tail at some
point yeah I remember you you making
that point about psychology and feeling
that it was quite a profound realization
because I think a lot of these ideas
conversations can can become almost
unrooted from the human world of status
prestige and and then sort of then you
get some kind of incentives become
aligned with in any kind of network or
any kind of organization and then you're
then you can be in trouble very quickly
I mean ironically Eric Weinstein we did
a film with Eric Weinstein that we call
glitch to the origin of the IDW
and he talked about the dangers of
groupthink and how the IDW was a set of
disagreeable characters but then you've
got the paradox of when you create a
tribe of none tribal individuals what
then happens yeah well that's
interesting yeah maybe you know I used
virtual signaling as my example in the
last answer to ponder but tribalism is
probably the same kind of challenge or
facet of human psychology we are we to
deny our evolutionary residue of being a
tribal animal is is is foolish I mean
you that's it's probably just a truth
that we are again we have to do the same
sort of decision if you're gonna try to
stamp that out as some sort of just
always toxic and always problematic
feature or it's something that you could
at could you build a tribe a moral tribe
or an ethical tribe or a philosophical
tribe yeah I guess I'm less afraid of
the word tribal than probably a lot of
people I see commenting online and and
pointing out this tribalism it's a date
it's a powerful feature you know an
example that I think I've also used this
like something like tribalism I I want
to contend ok this is an open question
if it's if it's a morally neutral
phenomenon of the psychology of the type
of animal that we are if it is it's like
splitting the atom when you split the
atom with with a with a fission reaction
and a huge amount of energy comes out
you discover that that's it that's a
morally neutral thing that those are
just you know those are just quarks
splitting at some level and a bunch of
other quarks flying off of it and you
have choices of what you want to do with
that you've discovered something
incredibly powerful when you've
discovered fission or fusion either of
them you can put it on the back of the
spaceship and go explore the cosmos if
you want with it you could probably put
it in some kind of engine and engineer a
bunch of other machines around it and
try to cure cancer or you could put it
on the back of a warhead and go kill
each other
the splitting of the atom was morally
neutral it's all about how we apply it
and how we we we directed this is my
whole thing about sort of can you notice
that thing and then hijack it for some
ethical means this totally kicks the can
down the the road of the philosophical
questions that I'm really interested in
are of what our ethical means and these
big philosophical questions which I hope
it's more of the conversation in the IDW
but if if that analogy holds and the
tribal instinct of the human animal is a
powerful we know it's a powerful
psychological phenomenon that could lead
very quickly to off awful horror shows
and nightmares but could also lead very
quickly to to beautiful you know dreams
and fulfillment of our of potential and
exploration and all those lovely things
that you hope so do we have to again do
the same thing of just call it this call
it this necessary just evil and then and
then walk away from it totally I you
know I'm agnostic even to that point but
I think in to Eric's point probably
about what what you want in sort of in
any system you want a method of error
detection and correction David Deutsch
is my favorite thinker I think I tweeted
about him more than anyone else I'm a
huge fan of David Joyce's work and he
sort of pins that sentence as mate if
there's a commandment of the universe
that you could try to derive from the
universe itself and the famous is off
distinction it would be something like
that that sustaining and building the
systems to detect and correct errors of
course you have to decide what an error
is and that's a different philosophical
question is the most important thing and
for that Eric's right for thinkers you
what you want is an incubator that can
detect and correct errors and if it
becomes tribal and it has biases that
start building within it that it that
there's certain errors that just are
never detected maybe I'm pointing to
some of the errors of like you know
pretending that we're animals that
suddenly don't want sex because we're
sitting in an IDW room or something like
that you want you want an ability
to detect and correct errors and open
discussion in a culture of criticism is
is important to uphold so in that
respect
tribal thinking if it becomes if it
becomes unable to to correct itself is
is I would say an objective wrong and an
objective evil in the universe to sort
of borrow some more deutschen language
so yeah we have to be be careful of that
I don't know I don't know if Eric has
any kin you know any ideas about how to
contend with that in something like the
IDW conversation it has to be cared for
nurtured all the time and maybe there's
an overcorrection of inviting people
into the IDW who are obviously
politically different from from you in
order to try to sustain that which which
can which can go too far I mean you can
excuse of a masback quotes about be
careful not to open your mind so far
that it falls out or those kind of
things it's like you you can go a little
too far being like okay this person is
like totally different from me in every
other way so perfect they should be in
the room with me that might not be true
they might just be totally wrong and
they might not be open to correction and
they might have completely wrong ideas I
guess but what we need to be able to do
in that conversation is if it is a group
of people and we're imagining some sort
of room with an IDW sort of sign on the
door and you let someone in the room who
is is just fundamentally different than
you in the way they think and the way
they see things cool let them in the
room I get the I get the the the value
of having them in the room but once
they're in the room don't be afraid to
challenge them and push them on these
things and try to discover truth like I
said because there are there are ideas
and conjectures about the way the
universe is even in the moral sphere
that are that cannot coexist and when
they both cannot be right that's what I
hope what's exciting about oh come in
the room we're gonna we're gonna hash
this out we're gonna figure this out we
might not get to the bottom of it but
we're gonna record this and we're going
to do with
our long thing and we're gonna get into
it and maybe and maybe I think some of
the distaste comes from people watching
some of these IDW conversations and not
seeing enough of that it's a lot of like
giving a pass being like oh well you
know they think really different than
differently than me so that's why
they're here and it's like yeah they
think really different than differently
than you and you're right so go go hash
it out and maybe they're you know it
seems to be a little not enough of the
latter part of that recently maybe so
yeah the other big point was the
Pangburn fiasco I mean Pangburn
obviously put on the Sam Harris Jordan
Peterson event and then a few events in
Australia I think only one actually took
place and then they folded and obviously
there was some kind of inertia or sense
of forward momentum that was stopped
around that time of having all of the
IDW members on stage with each other
talking about things discussing things
but it's also interesting looking at the
the other financial draw or the other
financial blocks to having these
conversations because just just having
looked at from as someone who puts on
events as an organization that puts on
events we've looked at the financials
it's almost impossible to have what you
want to have for example would be a sort
of Jordan Peterson sam Harris or Eric
sam Harris Douglas Murray a few people
on stage it's very hard to get those
financials to work yet the speaking fees
are real so if you're talking about
market forces these are all people who
have kids trying to go to college and
they have house payments and they get
paid this is this is their life and
their job
I mean increasingly more and more for
authors the live show and is a big
revenue stream more than selling books
it's happening the same way even in
music it's like you only make this month
on Spotify but you go sell out shows
that's where you make money so yeah
that's a reality that we are contending
with in these things and is a real is a
real shame this is to your point about
the Weinsteins and saying that
intellectual Commerce what was the quote
that truth-seeking can't survive market
forces yeah that's
that's probably a really good concrete
example of if market forces you know
people's kids need to go to college and
they need to get paid on stage and you
can no one's going to spend $300 to go
see a hour-long event well you know yeah
like you said you've done the numbers so
trying to tackle that hurdle I don't
know what the answer will be there might
be technological ways to tackle it live
streaming maybe you can lower the ticket
prices we can as people like you and I
or sometimes entrepreneurs in that sense
you try to work out the numbers and
maybe there's solutions out there but
you're fighting against you're fighting
against a fighting against those market
forces in people's that are real for
people I don't know the right answer it
mean is that are people getting greedy
like that's a question that I think
we're going to also have to just contend
with and critics of the IDW who this
goes to that general point of bad
psychology and bad philosophy greed is
one of those things we all contend with
like how much money is too much money if
someone offers me five million dollars
to read an ad for a product that I don't
agree with on my podcast am I going to
read it well five million dollars
there's a lot of money I could tell you
right here being like no way but you put
that check in front of me and you know
we all should be like that's a real
tough know to say so you know it's again
there's there this isn't two casts the
seek for moral purity will be the death
of any movement so we shouldn't have
that we should acknowledge that these
are real factors and people need to get
paid but is there a limit is there a
point where someone's gotten paid enough
is there a point when you know the the
the importance of what's going to be
said on stage should be enough to sort
of lower the price yeah you know who am
i did who are any of us that save this
stuff but I think probably ignoring
these questions or having it at this
dark dirty secret in the intellectual
world it's probably a big mistake we
should talk about these things and be
honest about these things Sam I think
has been more recently and probably
rightfully so when when you're that
sought-after and you have a lot of of
people who you know you have a lot of
people asking for your attention just
setting a price of entry to get me in
the door
it's probably a decent filter to weed
out some of the wasting of your time
yeah but you could use that to justify
high fees to a certain degree and I
don't know yeah we're all we're all
contending with that maybe maybe what we
see a lot of times is this trajectory of
someone who seemingly organically comes
from nowhere and is everywhere doing
really good work and then they hit some
level where suddenly they stop
outputting new ideas that's probably and
they start if you were mentioning with
Jordan like how much can you tour this
one book before you just write maybe the
same book and then tour that one again
because you hit this level that you just
be incentives to create new ideas and
new innovative ideas is is unplugged at
some certain point that that's a real
shame that I think yeah that we're all
that probably has to be addressed and
talked about in some way yeah we I think
we all have to contend with that
something that I was really excited
about at the beginning of the sort of
the emergence of the IDW and I first
found out about through the Rubin report
and a couple of shows on on the Rubin
report I remember one with Ben Shapiro
and Jordan Peterson and another one with
Bret and Eric where you just really got
the sense of a conversation that was
going somewhere and because in implicit
in the way that the IDW is framed is
that people might change their minds
that you could you and I I haven't had
that same sense of excitement or I
haven't seen that same sense of
excitement in many of the conversations
that I've seen since especially with
those core group from from from the
beginning and and there's a kind of
aliveness to a conversation where
someone might change their minds or
their open-mindedly inquiring into
something and there's a curiosity and
there's an adult an evolving perspective
on both sides and I haven't felt that
kind of a live quality for many of the
discussions that I can remember probably
over the last few months or so yeah I
think I think I feel the same kind of I
you know I know a lot of these guys
personally and I basically keep saying I
you know I'm like write more books like
put something out put out an
thisis let's talk about it let's argue
about it yeah if some I don't know I
can't remember the last time I've seen
India in the conversation of mind change
in real time like that well maybe I've
seen some of them go the wrong the wrong
way actually I mean there's there's a
topic like abortion is out there that
gets tossed around a little bit in this
and there's totally it if the IDW is a
group of people and we have sort of the
same names in mind there are disparate
outcomes of that question that are just
there as a mess on the floor in that IDW
room there really ought to be looked at
and picked up because I think there
there are definitive right and wrong
answers in that space or definitive
better and worse questions to ask to
probe that that aren't even being asked
I mean Dave Rubin has been at the center
of a lot of the criticisms of the IDW
that we've seen especially in the last
few months I think and I actually have
an interview with him where I put a few
of those questions to him
because I have a look back at some of
the previous shows and I kind of agreed
with it's not it's not whether you have
certain people on your show I mean I
think you completely should have free
rein to have anyone and speak to anyone
but it's about whether you're giving the
audience enough perspective giving them
enough information to make up their
minds about who these people are and and
I think valuable questions can be asked
and and you mentioned about sort of that
the the need for self correction and I
we I think it's fair to say we've not
really seen that with with Dave Rubin
we've seen him get very very defensive
very very triggered by a lot of the the
criticism that he's getting yeah yeah he
yes he does not if you point out errors
he doesn't seem to take it he doesn't
seem to take it in good faith and maybe
it's not from everyone in good faith but
I have a lot of open questions about
watching what's happened with Dave Rubin
and I don't so I want to preface this
again whenever I talk about Dave I don't
mean this personally
I want I want to put out I interviewed
him for my film didn't make the cut but
he was gracious to give me his time and
I've met him a few times and he's a
really nice guy none of this is meant to
be a personal attack on on dave rubin
but i have open questions about watching
watching his sort of trajectory as you
said sort of in this conversation where
gosh I don't know a polite way to say
this but I wonder if we underestimated
the well there's the intellect and the
intelligence that maybe it takes to sort
of walk away from a tribe that you were
captivated by because suddenly you're in
the wilderness and it's a dark place and
maybe going back to sort of the the
tribal instincts we have the lure of
finding a new tribe you might not even
be conscious of it but is there because
it's safe there's safety in numbers and
it's dark in the wilderness and you want
to be near other warm animals who
provide all this protection and some
evolutionary way again like these things
are not unique today if these things are
not unique to any of us but they might
you know that things are not distributed
even evenly in the world and Dave might
have a high you know a potent version of
that in his own psychology I think
famously stand-up comics always sort of
get knocked for you know they're there
they just want validation it's like
they're their whole thing maybe he was
selected a little bit for this kind of
of entrenchment and and you know maybe
by accident he's got himself in trench
but talking about Dave Rubin in this way
as I think you and I are trying to do as
again I don't mean this to be dismissive
or some jerky thing to say but as a
cautionary tale that walking into the
wilderness and finding yourself in the
wilderness or as Dave would probably put
it he didn't go anywhere the left left
him or whatever finding yourself in the
wilderness is a vulnerable dangerous
spot to be and it's and it's and it's a
it's a time where maybe you could fall
you could fall into conspiracy theories
very easily in that state you could fall
into violence and that's that you could
fall into a lot of directions and
state that we again I don't mean this to
be condescending but I have compassion
for the I will just call it the mistake
that Dave has made of ending up well
hopefully not ending but being in the
place where he's in now because I think
we all I don't know how it would have
gone for me in the post 9/11 waking up
period that I had which was just much
earlier than Dave's to sort of some of
the lunacy on the left if I had Twitter
and I had a YouTube channel that I could
just start like this maybe I like what
we're all dave rubin on some level we
all have a little dave rubin in us and
maybe he was a bit unlucky just even
given the place where he lives he's in
Los Angeles and he could pick up the
phone and call Sam Harrison get him on
his first show and get a huge audience I
mean a lot of things had to fell in
place for Dave Rubin to be Dave Rubin it
probably would have been better for him
if he was just a kid in Minnesota
without those connections who would have
maybe gone through that initial I don't
know angst and like wanting to like
throw a middle finger up to the left
that abandoned him when maybe the
audience wasn't so big and maybe he
would have sorted some of these things
out and seen in the mirror a little bit
of like okay this this might feel good
for a minute but this is not this is not
where the real show it I was also a fan
of Dave Rubens show you know at the
beginning and enjoying a lot of these
conversations I think having a hunch
that he was in a vulnerable spot but I
remember pretty clearly the moment where
I was like man yeah like personally
offended by it so I will take this one
personally and that you could call this
one a bit of an attack but people like
you and I in this field of storytellers
trying to amplify this with the video
tools that we have here I take the job
really seriously I know it's you could
take it too seriously sometimes but I
take it really seriously that it's a
privilege to be able to have these
conversations and it's a huge
responsibility to be able to have these
conversations and to edit these things I
mean taking taking hours and hours of
footage of someone with really big ideas
that they've spent years crafting and
working out and being very careful about
the language they choose and then you
and I are the ones who have the
like tasks to try to deliver that to an
audience who might only have 10 minutes
in their car that's a I take it
seriously and so I do a ton of homework
if I'm gonna interview someone and I'm
doing this podcast now and I have these
people that I'm interviewing I read
their books I read articles I try to dig
in as much as I can I talk to friends
about it I batted it around with myself
I spend a lot of time before the first
question is asked with what you know
with doing my homework and it became
clear to me actually this this goes back
to one of your questions about tribalism
it was an interview with Amy Chua and
Amy Chua wrote a book called political
tribes that I absolutely loved and I
read it and learned a lot from it and it
and it shifted my thinking on actually
this question of tribalism I was
probably honing a lot of her influence
in my answer to you about tribalism as
maybe it's not this evil thing to stamp
out but actually something to understand
and we and we absolutely pretending it
doesn't exist is a huge fatal mistake
and has been a fatal mistake it's a
great book it's a short book I recommend
everyone reading it but I saw this
happen where it's actually Michael
Shermer who was another person who I
think who has made some mistakes but
Michael Shermer brought Amy Chua to Dave
Rubin because Michael read her book and
maybe also saw a lot of these things and
liked a lot of it and also realized he's
friends with Dave was like out Dave
really needs to hear this because Dave
you know Dave's making some mistakes
that this could really correct he like
brought her to the studio and when I
watched their interview it was Michael
and Amy and then I think he had Amy on
solo it was clear to me after five
minutes that Dave Reuben maybe he looked
at a Wikipedia article at best but
hadn't read the book hadn't done an
ounce of homework of this thing the
questions he was asking were so asinine
towards her that again has someone in
the industry who sits in his chair often
I was just offended by being like you
have this incredible intellect in front
of you and someone who did a lot of work
and you didn't even take the time to do
the homework to read her book and so on
a personal level I was offended by it
there might be some people who could get
away with that like a Joe Rogan could
just come in and wing it and he's
curious but Dave has
agenda on that show I don't care what he
says about I'm just talking to people if
you watch that well you maybe not even
agenda but he has an opinion a political
opinion which he's allowed to have but
if you're gonna ask the questions with
some with some narrative that you're
looking for her answer to fit into it's
just totally disingenuous to your guests
to treat them that way and so just on a
pure like filmmaker and promise to your
audience and your guests level I was I
was personally offended by that one of
my frustrations generally maybe with the
the corner of the IDW that Dave occupies
is that there is the the stereotype sort
of SJW nineteen year old girl with
purple hair and screaming about you know
systemic racism or something on college
campuses that rightfully should be
lampooned and criticized but there's
also an opposite version of that of the
19 year old usually boy wearing a bowtie
who like red one and Rand book and
thinks that libertarianism is like you
know is the only philosophy of the world
that they'll ever need in their life and
and they'll go about their that person
should also be Lampoon because it's
they're both incredibly we know lazy and
harmful ideological positions to be in
and so has Dave sort of allied with the
stereotype on the other side in some
ways certainly I don't want to cast
aspersions on his fans but it probably a
lot of them are also his fans there
there's a deeper end of the pool they're
like waiting in the shallow end I hope
for Dave's sake of his own intellectual
journey that he can break out of that
and continue to go but it's uh he's
found a lucrative shallow and say that I
share your concerns about it seeming
unfair to focus on on Dave but I think
the reason why the reason why I did the
interview in the way that I did and the
reason that I'm kind of interested to
return to it in the context of the IDW
is that that was as Dave said in the
interview with with me his his garage
was kind of the home of the IDW it's
where a lot of the initial connections
were made and it's where a lot so it is
the place where when there are
criticisms that the flaws in in Dave's
thinking and before
moments are then sort of massively
highlighted I think there's a few
different pieces that we can kind of
unpack and they're all very useful
learning experiences for for all of us
one of which is what happens when you
replace a high-resolution critique with
a low resolution critique and I think
that's something that's really important
for the IDW is how do you how do you how
do you find a path through that there's
sort of very complex arguments around
say sex and gender for example without
slipping into a low resolution critique
these are very difficult conversations
that have to be had at this sort of
higher level and as soon as you come
down to a low resolution partially true
critique of the left for example then
then your that that's a really dangerous
place to be yeah that's that's really
interesting yeah I like that I mean just
as the thought that popped into my mind
it would be impossible but it's like we
should somehow have like there should be
a podcast or a YouTube situation where
it's like impossible to only listen to
five minutes like if you start it your
hat you can't get out of but you can't
get out of it for at least half an hour
because I think that's a really astute
point though is you know a little
information could be a dangerous thing
it's famously like the this mount stupid
graph that you know you get a little
information and suddenly you think
you're a genius
you get a little and for more
information and you realize you got a
long way to go yeah yeah you could you
could misunderstand and misinterpret
really big ideas that are so it's like
splitting the atom again it's like you
could you can make some monumental
mistakes if you miss understand I've
been looking at you know Darwin and
Darwinian ISM and the mistakes that
people make about understanding
evolution if you hear survival of the
fittest and then you walk away and you
think you know what that means and you
go run with it you can you can make a
horror show on earth pretty quickly
because that idea is even wrong but even
to just to know what's wrong about it
takes a long time I think actually you
know that's why someone like Sam Harris
who I love obviously I work with he's
not he's an incredible we need more
communicators of these
Sam Sam is a philosophy communicator the
way that Carl Sagan was a bit of a
scientist that really a science educator
because he had this incredible ability
to study and understand big complicated
ideas of science and then deliver it
within a pretty concise way that was
entertaining and poetic and really would
do the job
Sam is incredibly good at that I mean
writing a book on determinism he's he's
not he is not the first one he's like
the millionth and a half one to say that
free will is an illusion but he wrote a
really cool short book about it and
shorter than a lot of the other books
out there on it and there's a there's a
real talent in that I would say the
moral landscape is probably you know his
original thesis that that deserves
critique as an original idea but most of
his books and most of his work is
incredible philosophy communication and
that that's a really valuable skill and
we need more of that especially maybe in
this you know attention span as you were
pointing out earlier the incentives of
traditional media where you only have
you know a minute to speak if you can if
you can compress sort of you know
hundreds of years of philosophical
thinking into into a compressible thing
that's that's a really really good skill
but of course there are really bad ways
to do it there's bad ways to make a
low-resolution version of a file where
you actually miss all the good stuff
whether it's an image that just becomes
so pixelated that you can't see what
you're looking at anymore or you know it
but there's really good ways to do it
whatever algorithm turns you know a five
gig wave into a hundred Meg mp3 and
still sounds really good that algorithm
is in tremendously valuable tool and if
you if that analogy works with almost
the people who become the algorithms
that could take you know terabytes of
information and compress it and deliver
it to you but that's not always doable
or easy and we Nate we might not be
there yet
where you might need a three-hour long
podcast or four nights with Sam Harris
and Jordan Peterson talking about truth
and never getting anywhere and I think
they probably needed four more nights
and they needed and that's great but
that you know okay that sometimes that's
the best we can do is you're not going
to get this in five
you're not gonna get this in a minute
because I don't get this in a minute so
you know if I think Einstein has a lot
of great quotes about that something
like if you don't understand it if you
can't explain it simply you don't
understand it some all this kind of
stuff or whatever but yeah there it's a
it's a really really crucial important
point and maybe that's again the day of
Reuben criticism of like you know you do
more homework it's the the low the low
resolution sort of you know ben shapiro
owns and SJW is not helping anyone so i
want to kind of wrap up by coming back
to a point that you may write at the
beginning which was the difference
between politics or that your concerns
about the IDW was that whether it was a
political thing rather than a
philosophical thing and yeah that's a
really interesting point because the
nature of politics comes if you sort of
break it down it's not an inquiry it's
it's when inquiry stops it's it's got an
agenda it's got an end it's like when
one inquiry collapses into activism or
collapses into politics it lacks that
kind of a live sense of curiosity and
openness and and evolution and that's
not even that's not even - not that is
what politics is it's like we sat in the
room we thought about this or we did the
studies and we were going with this
answer and we're gonna try to push it
we're gonna try it out there in the
world and politics is how do we get
enough people to pull the lever so we
try this idea that's that is what
politics is you know I think like the
natural push back someone would have if
they hear a criticism of oh the IDW
shouldn't be political or is too
political or something as and I don't
even know if this is a good point
they'll point out like well look at all
these people with their disparate
political ideas and their disparate
political outcomes I think that's a
different point than the one I'm making
it is like if it's people who are have
political agendas no matter what they
are which on some some ways we all do
but if that's the practice of IDW is
pushing a political agenda or even
denigrating another political agenda
just for the sake of something else yeah
I think that's not only is it boring
it's it's just it's nothing it's nothing
new it's not a reaction to anything
that's probably that's what we were
doing before it's just it's just a
political reaction to a political
mistake and that's not that's not new
that's not like I don't think that's why
people came to the room
I think people came to the room because
they had a hunch that there was
questions that they couldn't ask and
there was answers that they thought were
out there or that there were answers
that they had a hunch where were you
know being pushed upon them that just
couldn't possibly be true whether on sex
and gender on all these big taboo topics
on religion and violence that was of
course a big one of this has nothing to
do with Islam that line became this
famous like I have a hunch that it has
something to do with this LOM let's talk
about what that something is and people
came to these rooms to to have open
discussions and ask questions that were
taboo they weren't about like hey pretty
sure the left is insane and don't you
agree with me it's like sure but it's
you know or it's like hey pretty sure
Trump is a liar and don't you agree with
me yeah that's nothing new that's just a
new that's a new political you know Club
to get together it's like a it's a book
club where you all read the same book
and you want to go talk about it there's
a value to that but it's not I don't
think that's like a sustainable you know
movement in there at you know my effort
is to make philosophy cool and fun and
and in and she'll also to deliver as
we're talking about to deliver to people
who don't who think philosophy is some
highfalutin word that they talk about on
college campuses and it's not for me I'm
trying to and I think in a lot of ways
the IDW in its early stages did do a lot
of that introduction to people of like
oh wait no there's actually this is
philosophy this is cool like it's it's
not just pie in the sky stuff and it has
real-life implications and it can change
my mind about things and if you're in it
for the self-help aspect there's plenty
of that if you want to extract that from
it but you know on the show I do with
Coleman now talking about you know
should you save the Mona Lisa or a
person in a fire or one of our upcoming
episodes is a couple that wants to
intentionally select genetically
engineer a deaf
to be in the world are these ethical
decisions like really big crazy fun
stuff that you know I hope I hope like
the the the barriers that were that
people were feeling were there the
barriers that they they were feeling on
their college campuses were there the
barriers that they were feeling on the
media were there the barriers that might
be there because of the incentives of
commercialism and capitalism and on Main
Street and you know on the popular media
I hope all of it once all those barriers
are down there's all there's very
intellectual barriers also really should
be should be brought down as well but I
don't know I don't know if we're
delivering on that promise or not I I
hope we're trying to reinvestigate it
and do you want to talk a little bit
about the the app that you're that
you're making at the moment because
because that's a really interesting
segue between the IDW is these sort of
people on a stage or kind of well known
figures and how how other people can
join this kind of intellectual awakening
yeah what there's a cool I mean people
might be familiar with the founding
story of it at this point I met Ryan
Bennett this is my partner with this
with this new program that we're
launching in the middle of the Pangburn
collapse it was sort of just one of
these random internet connections that
happens where the the famous penguin
Fiasco where they were gonna do this
huge show in New York and all these
tickets were sold and then famously two
days before the event he sends out an
email saying he folded the company and
anyway huge fiasco but suddenly people
were coming to New York and who all were
sort of in this space on some level they
were coming to hear the likes of Jordan
and Sam and all these names that we know
and we a bunch of us sort of organically
got together being like can we do
anything for these people like we have
these contacts like they're all coming
here let's do something I think Ryan put
out a random like Eventbrite tweet he
was one of the many who had bought a
ticket who couldn't cancel it he was
coming anyway i retweeted it one of
those random little viral moments and I
reached out to Ryan anyway when I met
him we just became fast friends famously
the Pangburn event that didn't happen
turned into this kind of impromptu party
in Manhattan
with at bars and at different places and
there was some skyping that came in with
some of the figures like Eric Weinstein
who talked to people when he could from
afar and Coleman was there Coleman
Hughes and you know probably no surprise
to anyone so many people came away
saying like this was better than the if
the event had even happened because on
some level you buy a ticket to go see
Sam Harris or or Erik Weinstein or
whatever and you kind of know what
they're gonna say it's like going to see
your favorite musician and like oh he's
playing as great as hits again and it's
great it's great to hear maybe real
improv a little this time and do
something new or here's a new song it's
great but really you're there in so many
ways to like be with other people who
are also have their ear to the ground of
this conversation and so what what we
launched was and then and then to finish
that maybe frustration is then the event
ends and everyone goes home and it seems
like the only thing to do is maybe like
yell about it on Twitter and that's
about it and it's we're seeming we were
missing something to connect the people
to change the conversation from the
one-to-many that happens when one
person's on a stage and many people are
out here to the many too many and how do
we do that so I think it's a really
simple idea we're calling it in common
and we just started doing some tests at
the Soho forum in New York which are
going well very early where it's pretty
simple you come to the event and you get
a code and it's a code that only people
at the event have access to and you sign
up for the code you answer just a few
simple questions of like when you're
available what kind of food you like to
eat what neighborhood you're in really
simple stuff we do all the algorithm
work behind the scenes and hook you up
with other people who went to the event
five or six people whatever it is you
there's Plus Ones and then you go and
have dinner with these people or brunch
and they launch it's in your
neighborhood and it's it's could be the
next day or a few days late or even on
the weekend and meet them and see what
happens and continue the conversation
and that's it it's just about it's
simple the work is up to you we'll just
connect you with it at the dinner table
and then you know make some friends and
error correct at the table if you want
to continue the discussion or talk about
whatever you want yeah it's in some ways
it's what meetup comm should have
we have a hunch the meetup.com effort is
sort of dissatisfying because there's
kind of no velvet rope
you know like who the hell is going to
show up at these things and weirdos from
the internet are gonna be there if you
if you're spending money to go see a
Jordyn Peterson talk and say can come
out of your night and so did these other
you know 400 or 500 people they got
through the velvet rope that might be
enough of a selection process that a you
might have a nice time at dinner with
them or maybe not and then we make it
really easy after the dinner to stay in
contact with the people you want to stay
in contact with it's totally private and
we keep all that sort of you know in
your control but it's a really simple
app and it's a really simple program
that we're just like I said we're in the
alpha-beta sort of mode of it called in
common hopefully yeah it does a lot of
good it's it's one of those simple but
eminently achievable technologically you
know achievable ideas that were like
let's let's just build it no one's built
this thing yet and so Brian's a really
good programmer and we're off to the
races so look for in common at events
that will be popping up a lot more in
2020 but yeah we're we're going through
that if you're in New York and you come
to the Soho forum you might see it I
think the next debate is about Bitcoin
or something so I'm sure we'll get a
bunch of people if you want to go have
dinner and talk to people a Bitcoin I'm
sure isn't that just any dinner party
pretty much anywhere yeah that's
actually just Brooklyn now at this point
is likely who someone will bring up
Bitcoin and then you'll fight about it
so but yeah it's right Ryan's great so
we're hoping to yeah cool I hope it
works yeah me too
yeah real real pleasure to speak to you
and catch up again soon yeah thanks man
that was fun
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon
you